Joseph Farris Cartoons
Joseph Farris Cartoons
1950-1969
Farris, Joseph.
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American cartoonist. Consists of original cartoons arranged alphabetically by periodical in which they appeared.
148974
Biographical History
Joseph G. Farris (1924- ) is an award-winning American cartoonist. Born in Newark, New Jersey, he grew up in Connecticut and in his teens took art classes from The New Yorker and Esquire cartoonist Rich Taylor. Farris served in the army for three years during World War II and was awarded a bronze star. He contributed several cartoons to Stars and Stripes. Back in Connecticut as a civilian, Farris continued his art training by attending the Whitney School of Fine Art in New Haven.
A contract cartoonist with The New Yorker since 1971, his work has also appeared in numerous daily papers and weekly magazines, including Collier's, Ladies Home Journal, McCall's, New York Times Book Review, Playboy, Punch, Redbook, and the Saturday Evening Post. For almost twenty years his cartoons were featured in Stern magazine in Germany. He has had two syndicated features (FarrisWheel, a daily panel for the Chicago Tribune Syndicate (1971-1974) and Phipps for United Features Syndicate) and has published several collections of his own cartoons, as well as appearing in cartoon anthologies including a compilation of UFO cartoons called UFO Ho Ho. He has done covers for The New Yorker, Barron's, Harvard Magazine, ABA Journal and many others, and his work is held in both public and private permanent collections. Farris also pursues sculpture and painting.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joseph G. Farris Cartoons consists of more than 175 original cartoons, including a few unpublished ones. The majority were published in American magazines but there are also a few from magazines in Germany and England. The single-panel gag cartoons are black and white pencil or pen-and-ink drawings with watercolor shadings. Themes consist of general American humor, including dating, work, families, and so on; UFOs and aliens also appear regularly.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are listed alphabetically by publication in which they appeared. Miscellaneous unpublished cartoons and foreign cartoons are listed at the end.
Related Material
has collections of more than one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Cartoonists; Farris, Joseph.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph G. Farris, 1967, 1969.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - Air Force - Space Digest, 1964-1967; 6 cartoons (Box 1)
  - American Artist, undated; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - American Express, 1960; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - American Legion, 1956-1957; 6 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - American Magazine, 1952-1954; 1959-1961; 12 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - American Management, 1966; 1 cartoon (Oversize 1)
  - Artists Magazine, 1965; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Blue Book, 1952-1955; 7 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - The Bulletin, 1953; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Cartoons and Gags, 1960; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Cavalier, 1962-1963; 2 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Chain Store Age, 1954; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Chicago Tribune
    - 1959, 2 cartoons (Box 1)
    - 1960, 7 cartoons (Box 1)
    - 1961, 15 cartoons (Box 1)
    - 1962, 14 cartoons (Box 1)
    - 1963, 12 cartoons (Box 1)
    - 1965, 1 cartoon (Box 1)
    - 1966, 11 cartoon (Box 1)
    - 1967, 36 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1960-1966; 29 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Climax, 1962; 1964; 2 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Collier's, 1953-1956; 4 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Commerce, 1954; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Compact, 1954; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Con Ed BDD&O, 1962; 1965; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Consumer Reports, 1967; 1 cartoon (Oversize 1)
  - DAC News, 1958-1964; 10 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Doctor's Wife, 1960; 3 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Ethyl News, 1960; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Family Weekly, 1955; 1960; 4 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Field and Stream, undated; 1 cartoon (Oversize 1)
  - The Fisherman, 1957; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - George Matthew Adams Service, 1956-1958; 20 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Golf Magazine, 1958-1960; 19 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Good Housekeeping, 1962; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Gourmet, 1961; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Harper's Magazine, 1964; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Hilton Carte Blanche, 1960; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Horticulture, 1958-1960; 4 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Intercom, 1956-1961; 9 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis, 1958; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Ladies Home Journal, 1963; 1965; 3 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Leisure, 1957; 1959; 3 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Look, 1956; 5 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Maclean's, 1954-1959; 13 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Marriage, 1959-1962; 15 cartoons (Box 1)
  - McCall's, 1957; undated; 4 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - McNaught Syndicate, 1967; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Medical Economics, 1957-1963; 13 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Men, 1956; 3 cartoons (Box 1)
  - National Observer, 1962; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - New York Times Book Review, 1953-1964; 33 cartoons (Oversize 3)
  - New Yorker, 1966-1969; 4 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Nugget, 1957-1958; 1963; 3 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Olds Rocket Guide, 1961; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Oregonian, 1955; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Penney News, undated; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Plymouth Traveler, 1960-1962; 15 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Popular Home, 1956; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Popular House, 1957; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Popular Mechanics, 1961-1961; 5 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Practical English, 1965-1966; 5 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Punch, 1958-1962; 23 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Redbook, 1954-1962; 14 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Report, undated; 1 cartoon (Box 1)
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1953-1967; 34 cartoons (Oversize 3)
  - Saturday Review, 1957-1966; 35 cartoons (Oversize 1)
  - Scholastic, 1959-1967; includes Scholastic, Scholastic Teacher, Senior Scholastic, Scholastic Review; 42 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - School Management, 1966-1967; 4 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Science World, 1962-1963; 1967; 4 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Ski, 1962; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Sports Illustrated, 1954; 1 cartoon (Oversize 2)
  - Star Weekly, 1953; 1955,; 1957-1958,; 1962; 9 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Town Journal, 1953; 1955; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - True Adventures, 1960; 3 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - TV Guide, 1965-1966; 8 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Washingtonian, undated; 5 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Weekend, 1957; 7 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Weekend (Canada), undated; 3 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Woman's Home Companion, 1956; 3 cartoons (Box 1)
  - World Week, undated; 2 cartoons (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified, 1950-1969; 19 cartoons (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous foreign magazines, 1950-1969; 36 cartoons (Box 1)
    See also Weekend (Canada)